Let's say you're trying to lose 20 pounds,
or boost your immunity,
or increase your ability to fight COVID,
or even cancer.
Well, the amazing thing is,
with the right diet,
you're well on your way to
achieving these vital health goals.
Welcome to the Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I'm your host, Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, it’s all 3MCPD
– all the time.
And if you’re wondering what
in the world I’m talking about,
all you need to know is one word
– chlorohydrin.
It’s a compound found in items like
Bragg’s Liquid Aminos and soy sauce.
But is it safe? Let’s find out.
In 1978, chlorohydrins were
found in protein hydrolysates.
What does that mean?
Proteins can be broken
down into amino acids
using a chemical process
called hydrolysis,
and free amino acids like glutamate
can have taste-enhancing qualities.
That's how they make cheap soy sauce
and seasonings like Bragg's liquid aminos.
This process requires high heat,
high pressure, and hydrochloric acid
to break apart the protein.
The problem is that when any residual
fat is exposed to these conditions,
it can form toxic compounds
called chlorohydrins.
But when I say toxic, we're talking
about toxic to mice and rats.
Chlorohydrins like 3-MCPD are
considered a worldwide problem
of food chemistry,
but no clinical studies on humans
have been reported so far.
The concern is about detrimental
effects on kidneys and fertility.
In fact, there was a time in which
it was considered as a potential
male contraceptive because it
could so affect sperm production.
However, research funding
was withdrawn
after unacceptable side-effects
were observed in primates.
They found flaccid testes in rats,
which is what they were going for,
but it caused neurological
scars in monkeys.
What do you do, though, when
there are no studies in humans?
How do you set some kind of
safety factor? Well, it's not easy.
What you do is take the lowest-observed-
adverse-effect level in animal studies,
which in this case was kidney damage,
then add in some kind of fudge factor,
and arrive at an estimated
tolerable daily intake,
which for 3-MCPD means
that high level consumers
of soy sauce may
exceed the limit.
But this was based on extraordinarily
high contamination levels.
Since then, Europe introduced a
regulatory limit of 20 parts per billion
of 3-MCPD in hydrolyzed
vegetable protein products
like liquid aminos and soy sauce.
The U.S. standards are much laxer,
though, allowing 50 times more:
1,000 parts per billion.
I called Bragg's to see where they fell,
and the good news is that they are doing
independent third-party analysis
of their liquid aminos for 3-MCPD.
The bad news is that despite my
pleas that they be fully transparent,
they wouldn't let me share
the results with you.
I've seen them though, but I'm only
allowed to confirm they comfortably
meet the U.S. standards, but
fail the European standards.
This is just the start
of the 3-MCPD story.
If you test people's urine
for 3-MCPD or its metabolites,
100% of people turn up positive,
confirming that it's
a widespread food contaminant.
I mean, 100% of people aren't downing
soy sauce or liquid aminos every day.
But remember, the chemical resulted from
a reaction with residual vegetable oil.
When vegetable oil itself is refined,
when it's deodorized and bleached,
those conditions also lead
to the formation of 3-MCPD.
And indeed, we've known for years
that various foods are contaminated.
In what kind of foods have these kinds
of chemicals been detected?
Well, if it's in the oils and fats,
then it's in the greasy foods
made from them: margarine,
baked goods, pastries,
deep-fried foods, and fatty snacks
like potato and corn chips,
as well as infant formula.
Here's the FDA limit
for soy sauce, a thousand,
but doughnuts can have more
than 1,200, salami more than1,500,
ham nearly 3,000, and
French fries in excess of 6,000.
So most people don't have
to worry about this problem
unless you're a consumer
of fried food. For example,
someone weighing about 150 pounds
who eats 116 grams of doughnuts
would exceed the maximum
tolerable daily intake,
even if that was their
only source of exposure.
Now, that's about two doughnuts,
but the same limit-blowing amount
of 3-MCPD could be found
in only five French fries.
In our final story, we learn about
another reason to avoid palm oil
and we question the authenticity
of extra-virgin olive oil.
Palm oil is the most commonly used
vegetable oil in the world today.
Pick up any package of processed
junk in a box, bag, bottle, or jar,
and odds are it will have palm oil.
Not only does it contain the primary
cholesterol-raising saturated fat
found mostly in meat and dairy, concerns
have been raised about the safety of
palm oil, given the finding that it
may contain a potentially toxic
chemical contaminant known as
3-monochloropropane-1, 2-diol,
otherwise known as 3-MCPD,
which is formed during
the heat treatment involved in
the refining of vegetable oils.
So these contaminants
end up being widespread
in refined vegetable oils and fats,
and any products that contain them,
including infant formulas.
It's been found in all refined vegetable
oils, but some are worse than others.
The lowest levels of the toxic
contaminants were found in canola oil,
and the highest levels in palm oil.
Based on the available data, this
may result in a signidicant amount
of human exposure, especially when used
to deep fry salty foods like French fries.
In fact, just five fries could blow
through the tolerable daily intake.
Now, if you just do this once in
a while, it shouldn't be a problem,
but if you're eating fries every day
or so, this could definitely be
a health concern. Because
the daily upper limit is based
on body weight, particularly high
exposure values were calculated
for infants who were on formula
rather than breast milk,
since formula is made from refined oils,
which—according to the European
Food Safety Authority—
may present a health risk.
And estimated U.S. infant exposures
may be three to four times worse.
If infants don't get breast milk,
there's basically no alternative to
industrially produced infant formula.
Given that fact, the vegetable oil
industry needs to find a way
to reduce the levels of these
contaminants, and in the meanwhile,
this is yet another reason
that breast is always best.
What can adults do to avoid exposure?
Well, if these chemicals are created
in the refining process of oils,
what about sticking to unrefined oils?
Refined oils have up to 32 times
the 3-MCPD compared to
their nonrefined counterparts,
with the exception
of toasted sesame oil.
Sesame oil is unrefined—they
just squeeze the seeds—
but because they are
squeezing toasted sesame,
the 3-MCPD may have
come pre-formed.
Virgin oils are by definition unrefined.
They haven't been deodorized---the process
by which most of the 3-MCPD is formed.
In fact, that's how you can
discriminate between the various
processing grades of olive oil.
If your so-called extra virgin olive oil
contains MCPD, then it must have been
diluted with some refined olive oil.
The ease of adulterating extra virgin
olive oil, the dificulty of detection,
the economic drivers, and
the lack of control measures
contribute to the susceptibility
of extra virgin olive oil to fraud.
How widespread a problem is it?
Of the 88 bottles off store
shelves tested, labeled
extra virgin olive oil, only 33
were found to be authentic.
Okay, but what if you stick to
the top-selling imported brands
of extra virgin olive oil? Seventy-three
percent of those samples failed.
Only about one in four
appeared to be genuine,
and not a single brand had even
half their samples pass the test.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social media
to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts Podcast
landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics
you can order the e-book, audio book,
or hard copy of my latest book
“How to Survive a Pandemic.”
For recipes, check out my
“How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Which is my latest-latest book.
It’s beautifully designed, with more than 100
recipes for delicious and nutritious meals.
All the proceeds I receive from
the sales of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the website is free.
There’s no ads, no corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.